Eugenio María de Hostos and Eugenio Carlos de Hostos Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Eugenio María de Hostos and Eugenio Carlos de Hostos Papers 1865-1990 (bulk 1870-1959)
MSS65392
Hostos, Eugenio María de, 1839-1903
Hostos, Eugenio Carlos de, 1879-1959
7,000 items
20 containers
8 linear feet
1 microfilm reel
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Eugenio María de Hostos, Puerto Rican nationalist, writer, and educator and his son, Eugenio Carlos de Hostos, military officer. Correspondence, family papers, photographs, miscellaneous papers, a diary of Eugenio María de Hostos, and papers relating to the renovation of the castle of Sotomayor in Pontevedra, Spain.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Betances, Ramón Emeterio, 1827-1898--Correspondence.; Bosch, Juan, 1909-2001--Correspondence.; Henríquez i Carvajal, Federico, 1848-1952--Correspondence.; Hostos family--Correspondence.; Hostos family.; Hostos, Eugenio Carlos de, 1879-1959. Eugenio María de Hostos and Eugenio Carlos de Hostos papers. 1865-1990.; Hostos, Eugenio María de, 1839-1903. Eugenio María de Hostos and Eugenio Carlos de Hostos papers. 1865-1990.; Luperón, Gregorio, 1839-1897--Correspondence.; MacCormick family--Correspondence.; Muñoz Rivera, Luis, 1859-1916--Correspondence.; Noble family--Correspondence.
Organizations
United States. Army--Intelligence specialists.; United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 65th.
Subjects
World War, 1914-1918--Colombia.; World War, 1914-1918--Guatemala.; World War, 1914-1918--Military intelligence--United States.; World War, 1914-1918--Panama.
Places
Cuba--History.; Dominican Republic--History.; Puerto Rico--Foreign relations--Spain.; Puerto Rico--Foreign relations--United States.; Puerto Rico--History--1898-1952.; Puerto Rico--History--To 1898.; Sotomayor (Pontevedra, Spain)--History.; Spain--Foreign relations--Puerto Rico.; Spain--History--Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain--Social life and customs--20th century.; United States--Foreign relations--Puerto Rico.
Titles
Eugenio Carlos de Hostos papers; Eugenio María de Hostos papers
Occupations
Authors.; Educators.; Nationalists--Puerto Rico
Provenance
The papers of Eugenio María de Hostos, Puerto Rican nationalist, writer, and educator, and Eugenio Carlos de Hostos, military officer, were given to the Library of Congress by Gloria de Alvear y de Hostos in 1999 (see letter appended to this register in the Manuscript Division Reading Room). A diary of Eugenio María de Hostos, which was microfilmed with the permission of Adolfo de Hostos and accessioned by the Library in 1954, was incorporated into these papers during processing. Additional papers of Eugenio Carlos de Hostos were given to the Library of Congress by Gloria de Alvear y de Hostos in 2006.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Eugenio María de Hostos and Eugenio Carlos de Hostos are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on one reel. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Biographical Note
Eugenio María de Hostos
Date Event
1839, Jan. 11 Born, Mayagüez, Puerto Rico
1852 Studied at the Institute of Bilbao and the University of Madrid, Madrid, Spain
1860 J.D., Central University of Madrid Law School, Madrid, Spain
1860 1869 Active in Spanish politics, advocating the independence of Puerto Rico and Cuba
1863 Published La peregrinacion de Bayoán. Madrid: Imprenta del Comercio
1869 Banished from Spain after denouncing Emelio Castelar, Spain’s first republican president, for refusing to grant independence to Puerto Rico and Cuba Emigrated to the United States and became editor of La revolución, newspaper of the Cuban Revolutionary Junta of pro-independence Cuban exiles in New York City
1870 Toured South America to generate support for the Puerto Rican and Cuban independence movements and to promote education reforms
1871? 1874? Teacher, University of Chile, Santiago, Chile
1872 Published Hamlet: ensayo crítico. Santiago: Imprenta de Ferrocarril
1875 Editor, Las tres Antillas, Dominican Republic
1877 Married Belinda Otilia de Ayala, daughter of a Cuban emigré, in Venezuela
1880 1888 Inspector general of public instruction, Dominican Republic
1887 Published Lecciones de derecho constitucional. Santo Domingo: Cuna de América
1888 Published Moral social. Santo Domingo: Imprenta de Garcia Hermanos
1888 1890 Headmaster, Miguel Luis Amunátequi secondary school, Chile
1890 1898 Professor, University of Chile, Santiago, Chile
1895 Published Geografía evolutiva. Santiago de Chile: R. Miranda
1898 Returned to Puerto Rico to work for Puerto Rican and Cuban independence Formed the League of Puerto Rican Patriots
1899 Led commission to President William McKinley to ask for Puerto Rican freedom
1903, Aug. 11 Died, Santo Domingo, Dominican Republic
Eugenio Carlos de Hostos
Date Event
1879, Aug. 26 Born, Santo Domingo, Dominican Republic, son of Eugenio María de Hostos
1896 Graduated, University of Chile, Santiago, Chile
1898 Graduated, Chilean Army Military Academy
1901 Graduated, University of Santo Domingo Law School, Dominican Republic
1905 Second Lieutenant, Porto Rico Regiment of Infantry, U.S. Army
1906 Promoted to first lieutenant
1913 1916 Aide-de-camp to the governor of Puerto Rico
1914 Married Josefa Adela (“Mignon”) MacCormick (died 1958)
1916 Promoted to captain
1917 1919 Stationed at Camp E. S. Otis, Panama Canal Zone, with the Porto Rico Regiment of Infantry. Military Intelligence Service, missions to Columbia, Chiriqui, Panama Republic, and Guatemala. Commanding officer, 1918
1918 1919 Promoted to major, then to lieutenant colonel and made battalion commander
1919 Returned to Puerto Rico with the Porto Rico Regiment of Infantry
1924 Reserve officer, U.S. Army
1935 Purchased as family home the castle of Sotomayor, Pontevedra, Spain
1940 Published with Adolfo de Hostos Indice hemero-bibliográfico de Eugenio María de Hostos. Havana: Cultural, s.a.
1952 Published Antología. Prólogo por Pedro Henríquez Ureña; selección, arreglo y apéndice por Eugenio Carlos de Hostos (editor). Madrid: Litografía y Encuadernación Published Hostos, hispanoamericanista: colección de ensayos acerca de Eugenio María de Hostos (editor). Madrid: Litografía y Encuadernación
1953 Published Eugenio María de Hostos, Promoter of Panamericanism. Madrid: Litografía y Encuadernación
1954 Published España y América. Prólogo por Francisco Elías de Tejada. Recopilación y arreglo por Eugenio Carlos de Hostos (editor). Paris: Ediciones Literarias y Artísticas
1959, May 27 Died, Madrid, Spain
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Eugenio María de Hostos (1839-1903) and Eugenio Carlos de Hostos (1879-1959) span the years 1865-1990, with the bulk of the material dating from 1870 to 1959. The papers are primarily in Spanish, but also in English and French, and are organized in two series, one dedicated to the father, Eugenio María de Hostos, and the other for the papers of the son, Eugenio Carlos de Hostos.
Eugenio María de Hostos was a Puerto Rican nationalist, writer, educator, and reformer. Born in Puerto Rico and educated in Spain, he also lived at times in the Dominican Republic, Chile, and New York City, moving frequently throughout his life depending on changing political circumstances. He was dedicated to the goal of an independent Puerto Rico, first from Spain and later from the United States, and the formation of a union of Antillean states to include Puerto Rico, Cuba, and the Dominican Republic. His papers contain correspondence with Caribbean nationalists such as Ramón Emeterio Betances and Gregorio Luperón as well as with various political organizations. Also included are family correspondence, microfilm of a diary, photographs, writings, and other papers. The news clippings, primarily published after his death, celebrate de Hostos’s legacy.
Eugenio Carlos de Hostos was the son of Eugenio María de Hostos. After a military education in Chile, the younger de Hostos became an officer in the Porto Rico Regiment of Infantry. This regiment had begun under Spanish rule and was incorporated into the U.S. Army after the Spanish-American War of 1898. In 1920 the name of the regiment became the 65th Regiment, U.S. Infantry. During World War I, the regiment was assigned to Panama to guard the canal against possible German attack. Material in the Porto Rico Regiment of Infantry file contains items relating to the military service of de Hostos and to his regiment in general, including correspondence, orders, news clippings, and photographs. De Hostos’s military career included work for the Army Intelligence Service traveling undercover in Colombia, Guatelama, and Panama to identify German activities in those countries during the war. His confidential reports are in this file, along with correspondence with Luis Muñoz Rivera, Puerto Rico’s resident commissioner in Washington, D.C.
In 1935, Eugenio Carlos de Hostos and his wife Mignon purchased an old castle and the surrounding estate in Sotomayor, Pontevedra, in the northwest corner of Spain, which would be their home for the remainder of their lives. The Sotomayor file documents management of the castle and in particular the restoration work the de Hostoses undertook. Also included are items concerning civilian life during the Spanish Civil War.
A large part of the Eugenio Carlos de Hostos series is composed of family papers. The file contains primarily correspondence, but also includes photographs, news clippings, and miscellanous papers. Both de Hostos and his wife corresponded regularly with their far-flung families living in the Dominican Republic, England, New York City, Puerto Rico, and Spain.
The rest of the series includes files on Eugenio Carlos de Hostos’ writings and editorial projects, mostly concerning the life and writings of his father, a file from his work as a representative of the Curtiss-Wright Export Corp in Spain in the mid-1930s, biographical material, photographs, and general correspondence. Notable correspondents include Juan Bosch and Federico Henríquez i Carvajal.
Additional material in the Eugenio Carlos de Hostos series includes correspondence, lists of catalogued books, family papers, financial records, legal papers, photographs, postcards, and Spanish ration books dating from 1943. Family papers consist of correspondence among de Hostos, MacCormick, and Noble family members, Sara de Hostos' school excercise books, and several diaries of Josefa "Mignon" de Hostos MacCormick. The financial records include documents submitted to various Spanish government agencies, bills and receipts, insurance policies, and bank records. Photographs document the 1958 wedding of Gloria de Alvear y de Hostos, granddaughter of Eugenio Carlos, and the 1939 centennial commemoration of the birth of Eugenio María de Hostos in San Juan, Puerto Rico.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in two series:
Eugenio María de Hostos, 1865-1990
Eugenio Carlos de Hostos, 1884-1990
Container List
- Eugenio María de Hostos, 1865-1990 (Box 1-2)
  Correspondence, diary, financial records, news clippings, printed matter, photographs, and writings.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material or name of individual or organization and chronologically therein.
  Diary available only on microfilm. Shelf no. 15,655
  - Auxiliadoro de la Independencia de Cuba, 1871 (Box 1)
  - Carreras, Carlos N., 1947-1951 (Box 1)
  - Club Cubano, New York, N.Y., 1870, undated (Box 1)
  - Club de la Liga Cubana, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Betances, Ramón Emeterio, 1892-1893 (Box 1)
    - Hostos, Eugenio Carlos de (Box 1)
      - Received from, 1890-1901 (Box 1)
      - Sent to, [1887?]-1901, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - Hostos, Rosa de, 1898-1899 (Box 1)
    - Luperón, Gregorio, 1885, 1895 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      - Family, 1898-1901 (Box 1)
      - Others, 1869-1902, undated, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1869-1903 Available only on microfilm. Shelf no. 15, 655 (Reel 1)
  - Financial material, 1893-1903 (Box 1)
  - Geography lessons, iundated (Box 1)
  - Liga de las Independientes, [1870?] (Box 1)
  - News clippings (Box 1)
    - 1903-1904, 1924-1946 (Box 1)
    - 1947-1981, undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1897-1899, 1941, 1953, 1967, 1977-1979, 1989, undated (Box 2)
  - Printed matter, 1939-1940, 1978-1990, undated (Box 2)
  - Sociedad de Subsidios para la Independencia de Cuba i Puerto Rico, 1872 (Box 2)
  - Writings, 1865-1877, 1935, 1946, 1959, undated (Box 2)
- Eugenio Carlos de Hostos, 1884-1990 (Box 2-20)
  Correspondence, family papers, financial records, legal papers, identification and travel documents, news clippings, photographs, and writings.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material or name of individual, organization or topic and chronologically therein.
  - Acknowledgment letters for gift books, 1935-1956 (Box 2)
  - Aloy, Miguel Angel, 1946-1957 (Box 3)
  - Aramburu family, 1928, 1937-1938, 1943-1946, undated (Box 3)
  - Asociación Española de Amigos de los Castillos, 1934-1955, undated (Box 3)
  - Balneario de Guitiriz (Spain?), 1946-1952 (Box 3)
  - Balseiro, José A., 1950-1958, undated (Box 3)
  - Biographical material, 1929-1932, 1942-1946, 1959, 1990, undated (Box 3)
  - Bosch, Juan, 1939, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Calling cards with notes, circa1888-circa1955 (Box 3)
  - Caruana, Jorge, Apostolic Nuncio in Cuba, 1940-1947 (Box 3)
  - Club memberships, 1901-1958 (Box 3)
  - Curtiss-Wright Export Corp., 1934-1936 (Box 3)
  - Daireaux, Max, 1945-1947, 1954-1956 (Box 3)
  - Family papers (Box 3)
    - Alvear de Hostos, Gloria ("Glorita"), 1943-1959, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Ayala de Hostos, Belinda (Box 3)
      - 1892-1904 (Box 3)
      - 1905-1919, undated, (8 folders) (Box 4)
    - Hostos, Adolfo de (Box 4)
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
        - 1900-1946 For additional material see Container 5 Bayoán de Hostos, correspondence, (7 folders) (Box 4)
        - 1947-1955, 1977, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - News clippings, 1917, 1939-1967, 1979, undated (Box 5)
      - Photographs, 1955, 1979, undated (Box 5)
    - Hostos, Bayoán de (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 1900-1911, 1928-1959, (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - News clippings, 1927-1928, 1945, 1952, undated (Box 5)
      - Photographs, undated (Box 5)
    - Hostos, Filipo de (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 1904-1919, 1928-1938, 1945-1959, undated, (4 folders) (Box 5)
      - News clippings, 1939, 1946-1953, 1969, undated (Box 5)
    - Hostos, Luisa Amelia de (Box 5)
      - Correspondence (Box 5)
        - 1891-1906, (3 folders) (Box 5)
        - 1907-1928, undated, (8 folders) (Box 6)
      - News clippings, 1916-1928, undated (Box 6)
    - Hostos, Mariangelina de, 1904-1912, 1923-1931, 1943-1959, undated (Box 6)
    - Hostos, Rosa de, 1897-1913, undated, (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - Hostos, Sara de (Box 6)
      - 1918-1939, (3 folders) (Box 6)
      - 1940-1977, undated, (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - MacCormick family, 1889-1907, 1915-1921, 1935, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - MacCormick, Gloria (Box 7)
      - 1929-1959, (4 folders) (Box 7)
      - Undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - MacCormick de Hostos, Josefa (“Mignon”) (Box 8)
      - Diary, 1918 (Box 8)
      - Correspondence (Box 8)
        - Hostos, Eugenio Carlos de, 1912-1919, 1927-1930, 1940-1955, undated, (5 folders) (Box 8)
        - General (Box 8)
          - 1917-1940, (2 folders) (Box 8)
          - 1941-1955, undated (Box 9)
      - Miscellany, 1919-1922, 1940, 1955-1958 (Box 9)
      - Passports, 1941-1952 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1903-1904, 1916, 1929-1959, undated (Box 9)
    - Noble family, 1918, 1928-1958, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Noble, Josephine (“Finy”), 1928-1953, undated, (3 folders) (Box 9)
  - Financial records, 1894-1908, 1914, 1921-1922, 1931-1955, 1971, undated (Box 10)
  - Genealogical material, circa 1920-circa 1962 (Box 10)
  - General correspondence (Box 10)
    - 1895-1933, (8 folders) (Box 10)
    - 1934-1952, (11 folders) (Box 11)
    - 1953-1959, undated, (5 folders) (Box 12)
  - Gran Peña, Madrid, Spain, 1933-1956 (Box 12)
  - Gun licenses, 1928, 1952-1958 (Box 12)
  - Guzmán, Manuel Rodríguez, 1903-1905, 1910-1920, 1932[?], (4 folders) (Box 12)
  - Henríquez i Carvajal, Federico, 1911-1941, 1950-1956, undated (Box 12)
  - Hogar Social Eugenio María de Hostos, Puerto Nuevo, Puerto Rico, 1953-1960, undated (Box 13)
  - Ibero-American Society, 1927-1928, undated (Box 13)
  - Identification and travel papers (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1924-1949, 1959 (Box 13)
    - Passports, 1941-1958 (Box 13)
  - Jones, Helen, 1930, 1945, 1955, 1962, undated (Box 13)
  - Legal papers, circa 1901-1904, 1916-1918, 1924, (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Lists for book distributions, 1939, 1950-1953, undated, (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Marqueses de Villa Alcazar, 1940-1955, undated (Box 14)
  - Miscellany, 1912-1941, 1950-1951, undated (Box 14)
  - News clippings, 1896-1959, undated, (3 folders) (Box 14)
  - Notebooks, 1903-1908, 1946-1952, undated (Box 14)
  - Orden de San Juan Bautista, 1929-1935, 1955, undated (Box 14)
  - Photographs, 1922-1960, 1980, undated, (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - Porto Rico Regiment of Infantry, U.S. Army (Box 15)
    - Correspondence and memoranda regarding U.S. policy toward the regiment, 1908-1924, undated (Box 15)
    - Military service of Eugenio Carlos de Hostos (Box 15)
      - General, 1897-1928, undated, (5 folders) (Box 15)
      - Intelligence reports (Box 15)
        - Colombia, 1917 (Box 15)
        - Guatemala, 1918 (Box 15)
        - Panama and the Canal Zone, 1917-1918, undated (Box 15)
    - News clippings, 1904-1924, undated (Box 15)
  - Postcards, circa 1905-circa 1955 (Box 15)
  - Serna, Luis de la, 1930, undated (Box 16)
  - Sotomayor, Pontevedra, Spain (Box 16)
    - Correspondence, 1935-1959, undated, (6 folders) (Box 16)
    - Financial records (Box 16)
      - Account books, 1935-1942 (Box 16)
      - Miscellany, 1935-1956, undated, (2 folders) (Box 16)
      - Taxes, 1935-1947 (Box 17)
    - Miscellany, 1937-1958, undated (Box 17)
    - Pedre, Christina de, 1955-1956 (Box 17)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 17)
    - Restoration project, 1939-1940 (Box 17)
    - Spanish Civil War, 1936-1942 (Box 17)
  - Student papers, 1884-circa 1902 (Box 17)
  - Wedding, 1913-1914 (Box 17)
  - Writings (Box 17)
    - Financial material, 1950-1959 (Box 17)
    - Newspaper, 1896-1907 (Box 17)
    - Notes about Eugenio María de Hostos, undated (Box 17)
  - Addition
    - Automobiles, 1942-1953 (Box 18)
    - Book lists, undated (Box 18)
    - Correspondence
      - Glaishier, Evie, 1942-1952 (Box 18)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1923-1962 (Box 18)
      - Sandford, Archie and Jean (Bank of London & South America Ltd.), 1942-1952 (Box 18)
    - Family papers
      - Hostos, Adolfo de, 1917-1975 (Box 18)
      - Hostos, Luisa Amelia de, 1911 (Box 18)
      - Hostos, Rosa de, 1904-1911 (Box 18)
      - Hostos, Sara de, 1924-1975, (2 folders) (Box 18)
      - MacCormick family, 1918-1960 (Box 18)
      - MacCormick, Gloria, 1928-1965 (Box 18)
      - MacCormick de Hostos, Josefa ("Mignon"), diaries, 1923, 1940 (Box 18)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1937-1977 (Box 18)
      - Noble, Arthur H., and C. L. Miro, 1925-1949, (2 folders) (Box 18)
      - Noble, Josephine ("Finy"), 1947-1953 (Box 18)
      - Poetry book, unattributed, 1928 (Box 19)
    - Financial records
      - Bills and receipts, 1935-1947, undated, (6 folders) (Box 19)
      - Book orders, 1934-1940 (Box 19)
      - Caja Nacional de Subsidios Familiares, 1938-1941 (Box 19)
      - Hotel bills, Spain and Portugal, 1942-1947 (Box 19)
      - Instituto de Credito para la Reconstruccion Nacional, 1939-1940 (Box 20)
      - Instituto Nacional de Prevision, 1934-1956, (3 folders) (Box 20)
      - Insurance policies, 1924-1950, (3 folders) (Box 20)
      - International transportation and customs, 1929, 1953-1955, (2 folders) (Box 20)
      - Miscellany, 1935-1950 (Box 20)
      - Rental, electric, and gas contracts, 1936-1947 (Box 20)
      - Royal Bank of Canada, 1934-1944, (2 folders) (Box 20)
    - Legal papers
      - A. Hartmann & Co., 1927-1935 (Box 20)
      - American Transmarine Co., lawsuit, 1923-1926 (Box 20)
      - Miss Nellie MacCormick Trust, 1938 (Box 20)
      - Rosales Farm lease, 1927-1928 (Box 20)
    - Menu and food notebooks, 1936 (Box 20)
    - Obituaries, 1894-1957 (Box 20)
    - Photographs, 1918, 1924, 1939, 1958-1959, undated, (2 folders) (Box 20)
    - Postcards, 1911-1982 (Box 20)
    - Ration books, Spain, 1943 (Box 20)